Okay, good morning, boker tov בוקר טוב *boker tov*. Today's daf דף
*daf* is yud-chet י"ח *yud-chet*, and we pick up at the bottom
of yud-chet amud bet י"ח עמוד ב *yud-chet amud bet*,
where Tanu Rabbanan תנו רבנן Tanu Rabbanan, *Tanu Rabbanan*, Beis Shammai omrim
ein mochrin בית שמאי Beis Shammai, אומרים אין מוכרין *Beis Shammai omrim
ein mochrin*, about ten lines from the bottom at the two dots.
So, we dealt with the whole issue about starting melacha מלאכה melacha
*melacha* before Shabbos שבת Shabbos *Shabbos* and having them continue into Shabbos
שבת Shabbos, *Shabbos*, where we explain that either based on shevisas keilim
שביתת כלים shvisas keilim, *shevisas keilim* or some type of d'rabbanan דרבנן
d'rabbanan, *d'rabbanan*, and then there were all these exceptions. Beis Hillel בית
הלל Beis Hillel, *Beis Hillel* agrees about a watermill because it's probably,
at least one explanation in the Gemara גמרא Gemara *Gemara* which is
also in the Yerushalmi ירושלמי *Yerushalmi*, is that it creates a large
amount of noise and it seems, it feels experientially like melacha מלאכה
melacha *melacha* is being done on Shabbos שבת Shabbos. *Shabbos*, and there
are cases Beis Shammai בית שמאי Beis Shammai, *Beis Shammai* himself agrees
to like k'dei tavad כדי תבא *k'dei tavad* and other types of
issues. Anyway, now we move on from things beginning before Shabbos שבת
Shabbos. *Shabbos* and continuing to doing things with a non-Jew before Shabbos
שבת Shabbos, *Shabbos*. Notice also the theme here for the first six
perakim פרקים *perakim* are erev Shabbos ערב שבת erev Shabbos, *erev Shabbos*
and leading into the actual things you do on Shabbos שבת Shabbos.
*Shabbos* itself, or don't do on Shabbos שבת Shabbos *Shabbos* itself, which
we'll get to later in the Maseches מסכת *Maseches*. So, one thing
you don't do here is, according to Beis Shammai בית שמאי Beis
Shammai, *Beis Shammai*, is you don't sell objects or help a non-Jew
load up his donkey or whatever right before Shabbos שבת Shabbos *Shabbos*
until he can get home, and Beis Hillel בית הלל Beis Hillel
*Beis Hillel* says you're allowed to do it. So, let's take a
look at the Gemara גמרא Gemara *Gemara*. So, the phrase in the
Mishna משנה Mishnah, *Mishna* was ella k'dei she-yagi'a l'makom karov אלא כדי
שיגיע למקום קרוב *ella k'dei she-yagi'a l'makom karov*, it says he not
home, he gets to a nearby place, and Beis Hillel בית הלל
Beis Hillel *Beis Hillel* says it's permissible. So, let's look what the
Gemara גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says. Tanu Rabbanan תנו רבנן Tanu Rabbanan *Tanu
Rabbanan*: Beis Shammai omrim v'lo yimkor adam cheftzo l'nochri בית שמאי Beis
Shammai, אומרים ולא ימכור אדם חפצו לנכרי *Beis Shammai omrim v'lo yimkor
adam cheftzo l'nochri*, don't sell your objects to a non-Jew, v'lo yash'ilenu
v'lo yalvenu v'lo yiten lo b'matana ולא ישאילנו ולא ילוונו ולא יתן
לו במתנה *v'lo yash'ilenu v'lo yalvenu v'lo yiten lo b'matana*, don't lend
it to him or don't give it to him as a gift,
ella k'dei she-yagi'a l'beiso אלא כדי שיגיע לביתו *ella k'dei she-yagi'a l'beiso*.
So, our Mishna משנה mishna *Mishna* said l'makom karov למקום קרוב *l'makom
karov*, but here the Baraisa ברייתא braita *Baraisa* is a little bit
clearer what that means; it says he has to be able to
get home. U-Beis Hillel omrim ובית הלל אומרים *u-Beis Hillel omrim*, Beis
Hillel בית הלל Beis Hillel? *Beis Hillel* says, k'dei she-yagi'a l'bayis hasamuch
lachoma כדי שיגיע לבית הסמוך לחומה *k'dei she-yagi'a l'bayis hasamuch lachoma*, to
get to the house at the wall at the edge of the
city. Now, this assumes that the non-Jew who's buying stuff from you
is going to a different city to bring it home, that his
home is in a different city.
And in fact, you know, I was reading in like, I think,
the Galil גליל *Galil*, it's certainly true that like the cities were
either, tended to be either like all Jewish or all non-Jewish except
for like certain, you know, very specific like metropolises, like major, you
know, cosmopolitan cities. So, it's not so unusual that the assumption here
is, is that if you're selling something to a non-Jew, he's leaving
the city and getting home. So, according to this, even Beis Hillel
בית הלל Beis Hillel *Beis Hillel* in principle agrees to Beis Shammai
בית שמאי Beis Shammai *Beis Shammai* that he has to leave the
city, maybe doesn't have to get all the way home but he
has to get to the next city to the house right by
the wall. U-Beis Hillel omrim ובית הלל אומרים *u-Beis Hillel omrim*, Beis
Hillel בית הלל Beis Hillel *Beis Hillel* says, I just said this,
Rabbi Akiva omer רבי עקיבא אומר *Rabbi Akiva omer*, Rabbi Akiva רבי
עקיבא *Rabbi Akiva* says, k'dei she-yeitzei mi-pesach beiso כדי שיצא מפתח ביתו
*k'dei she-yeitzei mi-pesach beiso*. No, it's not, you don't have to get
to the house in the beginning of the next city; as long
as the non-Jew leaves your house, you're okay. Amar Rabbi Yosi bar
Yehuda אמר רבי יוסי בר Rabbi Yose bar... יהודה *Amar Rabbi Yosi
bar Yehuda*, hein hein divrei Rabbi Akiva hein hein divrei Beis Hillel
הן הן דברי רבי עקיבא הן הן דברי בית הלל Beit Hillel,
*hein hein divrei Rabbi Akiva hein hein divrei Beis Hillel*. That Rabbi
Akiva רבי עקיבא *Rabbi Akiva* is not claiming that he's making a
third position; he is really stating what he believes Beis Hillel's בית
הלל Beit Hillel *Beis Hillel's* position to have been. Lo ba Rabbi
Akiva ella l'faresh divrei Beis Hillel לא בא רבי עקיבא אלא לפרש
דברי בית הלל Beit Hillel *lo ba Rabbi Akiva ella l'faresh divrei
Beis Hillel*. He's explaining Beis Hillel's בית הלל Beit Hillel *Beis Hillel's*
position, not so much explaining it since those words really don't fit
into bayis hasamuch lachoma בית הסמוך לחומה *bayis hasamuch lachoma*, but he's
really coming to explain that Beis Hillel בית הלל Beit Hillel, *Beis
Hillel* really was very lenient as long as he left the house.
And that actually sounds like our Mishna משנה mishna *Mishna* is based
on Rabbi Akiva's רבי עקיבא *Rabbi Akiva's* version because in our Mishna
משנה mishna *Mishna*, Beis Shammai בית שמאי Beis Shammai *Beis Shammai* says
makom karov מקום קרוב *makom karov*, which is also not exactly as
we have in the Tosefta תוספתא Tosefta *Tosefta*. Tosefta תוספתא Tosefta *Tosefta*
says to get to his home, and Beis Hillel בית הלל Beit
Hillel, *Beis Hillel* matirin מתירין *matirin* straight across the board they allow
it. So, here too, Rabbi Akiva רבי עקיבא *Rabbi Akiva*, that's much
closer to Rabbi Akiva רבי עקיבא *Rabbi Akiva* which says as long
as he leaves your house. Okay, so again the concern seems to
be here not something like shevisas keilim שביתת כלים shvisas keilim, *shevisas
keilim*. You can't even sort of like argue like it's a melacha
מלאכה melacha *melacha* that you have started that's continuing, because here you
sold it to a non-Jew and it's the non-Jew deciding to take
it home, it's now his object, it's no longer your interest. So,
it's not like you're sending a package via the non-Jew, you sold
it to the non-Jew. So here it seems just like a different
issue, that the non-Jew leaves your house with an object that used
to be yours erev Shabbos ערב שבת erev Shabbos, *erev Shabbos*, it
looks like from an appearance perspective like he is carrying this and
handling this for you on Shabbos שבת Shabbat *Shabbos*, and Beis Hillel
בית הלל Beit Hillel *Beis Hillel* and Beis Shammai בית שמאי Beis
Shammai *Beis Shammai* are concerned and Beis Hillel בית הלל *Beis Hillel*
is much more lenient. Now he asks, why is that wrong? To
have him do melacha מלאכה melacha, *melacha* for you on Shabbos שבת
Shabbat, *Shabbos*?
But we have Shabbos goys and all.
Well look, Shabbos goy is the exception. The general rule is you
can't, you know, like we see later in the Mishna משנה mishna
*Mishna*, you can't put like, drop your clothes off by the non-Jew
and say I need you to do this on Shabbos שבת Shabbat
*Shabbos*. You can't directly ask them to do a melacha מלאכה melacha
*melacha* for you on Shabbos שבת Shabbat.
*Shabbos*. But I'm giving it to him, it's now his.
I understand, so that's my point, is that this assumes number one,
that if he actually is doing the melacha מלאכה melacha *melacha* for
you specifically for you on Shabbos שבת Shabbat *Shabbos*, that's forbidden. It's
very implicit later in the Mishna משנה Mishnah: *Mishna* where it talks
about giving stuff to the non-Jew. Does he have enough... time to
get it done before שבת Shabbat like your clothes to be a
launderer? And then there's an assumption that, thank you, that even if
it looks like that, it's improper. But you're right, thank you, it's
definitely an extension of.
We're judging other Jews in a very bad way instead of saying
מלף דזכות melaf dizechus that you must have given it to him
because he's now, you know. Yeah, you never...
it's like everyone's going to be watching and oh, they'll see this,
this guy is carrying, you know, your coat. So you... if you
understand what I'm saying, you're judging other non-Jews.
Right.
Yeah, but don't... not any particular non-Jews. And there is a reality,
you know, I
understand, I mean there are,
I mean yeah, but not any particular... Right, but not any particular
Jews. You're just saying, you know, people are influenced by appearances and
that is a reality. So you're not pointing out this particular person,
we don't trust you, but there's a reality about the appearances. And
also I would say, you know, it's also part at some level
by שבת Shabbat, like about the experience you're creating. You know, and
how much at an experiential level even if you know the facts,
if you have all these, like, non-Jews carrying objects, you know, and
traveling in the, you know, right there on Friday night, there's like
some, something that doesn't feel so שבת-דיק. Shabbos-dik. I understand. Look, it's
a good thing, so at the end of the day you're siding,
fine, so you side with בית הלל, so that's fine, who we
פסק pasken like anyway. But you know, alright, but בית שמאי, Beis
Shammai you're right, that's a concern of בית שמאי, Beis Shammai yes.
But there isn't... if I see Rabbi Linzer eating at a restaurant,
I assume that it's kosher.
Right. So it's the flip side of
what we learned about מראית עין maris ayin as opposed to saying...
Alright, so that's the point. What Rivka is saying is that מראית
עין maris ayin assumes that people will draw natural conclusions and they
won't always be so much דן לכף זכות. dan le-chaf zechus. We're
not being דן אותם לכף זכות. dan osam le-chaf zechus. Okay, but
it's not a particular person, there's a reality, you know, people gossip
and they have perceptions and those things are reality. Anyway, that's בית
שמאי, Beis Shammai, we don't rule that way. So let's take a
look at a parallel discussion of בית שמאי, Beis Shammai. תנו רבנן,
Tanu Rabbanan. three lines from the bottom, בית שמאי אומרים לא ימכור
אדם חמצו לנכרי אלא אם כן יודע בו שיכלה קודם הפסח. Beis
Shammai omrim lo yimkor adam chametzo lenachri ela im kein yodeia bo
sheyichleh kodem ha-Pesach. Now this seems, דברי בית שמאי, divrei Beis Shammai,
that it's more than just perceptions, because
well, let's take... because well, let's see what it is. בית שמאי
Beis Shammai, says don't sell your חמץ chametz to a non-Jew unless
you know he has enough time to eat it before פסח Pesach
comes about, because you don't want him eating חמץ chametz that used
to be yours on פסח. Pesach.
You certainly don't do that today. Right.
ובית הלל אומרים כל זמן שמותר לאכול מותר למכור.
u-Beis
Hillel omrim
kol zman she-mutar le-echol mutar limkor. Now
as long as you can eat it, you can sell it to
him and you don't have to be concerned even if he winds
up eating it on פסח. Pesach. רבי יהודה אומר כותח הבבלי וכל
מיני כותח, Rabbi Yehuda omer kutach ha-Bavli ve-chol minei kutach, Babylonian כותח,
kutach, which is some type of a dip which had breadcrumbs and
all types of כותח, kutach, אסור למכור ל' יום קודם הפסח, assur
limkor lamed yom kodem ha-Pesach, you can't sell thirty days before פסח
Pesach
because that's a dip and people, you know, eat those over a
stretch period of time. So basically this sounds like he is going
according to the position of בית שמאי Beis Shammai and also and
just giving a specific example of this כותח הבבלי. kutach ha-Bavli. So
here you see that it's not just an issue about, you know,
about people thinking he's doing a מלאכה melacha, for you because what
do they think? They think the גוי Goy is eating your חמץ?
chametz? I mean the חמץ chametz is now in his house and
presumably they know that it's a non-Jew's as well. So it really
sounds if you combine these two that בית שמאי's Beis Shammai. idea,
and this is somewhat consistent with the idea of שביתת כלים, shvisas
keilim is that any process that somehow you began, you're responsible for,
and it's seen connected to you. So it's not a perception issue.
If I sell the non-Jew this thing and that leads him to
now carry it home on שבת, Shabbat, even though let's say everybody
knew the facts, not like we said before, perception, I started a
process which ultimately is culminating in this object, somebody carrying this object
on שבת. Shabbat, Now it's true, that person carrying it is a
non-Jew and it's not a violation, but because I'm involved in it,
it's somehow is this, I'm involved in it being carried on שבת.
Shabbat. And seems to be that's very similar to the idea we
had about the משנה, mishna you don't start a process like the,
you know, like the thing turning into ink or dyeing or whatever
ערב שבת, erev Shabbos. not because of שביתת כלים, shvisas keilim but
because if you begin a process and then it continues through שבת,
Shabbat, it's like at some level you are continuing to do it
through שבת. Shabbat? And then it also explains the חמץ chametz example,
you sold him the חמץ, chametz, but then it leads to the
fact that he's eating this חמץ chametz which is yours. So but
you, since you're the one that began this process, somehow you because
of you חמץ chametz is being eaten on פסח. Pesach. Although ironically
not by a person who's forbidden to eat it, by a non-Jew,
but it seems that that is where בית שמאי Beis Shammai. is
coming from. I don't know if it's biblical or presumably, you know,
it's rabbinic or, but nevertheless it seems like it's not appearances, it's
hard to make the appearances argument by the חמץ. chametz. And it
does seem much more like a responsibility for the ongoing process that
is being done. Of course the problem is there are cases where
בית שמאי Beis Shammai clearly allows it, like lighting candles ערב שבת,
erev Shabbos, putting your food on the fire ערב שבת. erev Shabbos.
Those are exceptions anyway as we mentioned yesterday. Yes Charlie?
Regarding the פסח Pesach issue, we are, where it says as long
as it's permitted for a Jew to eat... right... is that biblically
חמץ chametz or is it rabbinically?
Yes, and about a period where it's allowed to get הנאה hana'ah
but not to eat. Right, that's the fourth. All right, so let's
not worry about that, but you're right, you could make those distinctions.
All right, now let's keep on going, going, top of יט עמוד
א, yud tes amud aleph, תנו רבנן Tanu rabbanan: we taught: נותנים
מזונות לפני הכלב בחצר. notnim mezonos lifnei hakalev bechatzer.
You might like this because it's about feeding your pet. You can
give food to your dog in the courtyard on...
this is on פסח Pesach itself...
on שבת Shabbat, itself, not even ערב שבת, erev Shabbat you're allowed
to feed your dog. נטלו, netalo,
now if the dog picks it up ויצא veyatza and starts carrying
it out of the courtyard, אין נזקקין לו, ein nizkakim lo, then
you're not responsible for him. What? אי דכוחא דבבלי. I dekocha deBavli.
You were doing something else. אין נזקקין לו. ein nizkakim lo. כיוצא
בו, kayotzei vo, similarly... נותנים מזונות לפני הנכרי בחצר. notnim mezonos lifnei
hanachri bechatzer.
That you can give a... we're at the top of יט עמוד
א. yud tes amud aleph. Okay, yeah. נותנים מזונות לפני הנכרי בחצר.
notnim mezonos lifnei hanachri bechatzer. You can feed a non-Jew and give
him food in your courtyard, which is a רשות היחיד. reshus hayachid.
נטלו, netalo, if he picks it up ויצא veyatza and then he
leaves, אין נזקקין לו, ein nizkakim lo, you're not responsible for it
because you gave him the food. Now, the difference of these is,
and this is presumably even בית שמאי, Beis Shammai maybe בית הלל
you wouldn't have to say it, but this is presumably even בית
שמאי. Beit Shammai And that's what תוספות Tosafos says, אפילו בית שמאי.
afilu Beis Shammai. And why is it different? Because if I sell
you something right before שבת Shabbat, and you don't live in my
house, then of course I began a process which I know is
going to culminate with you, as I said, carrying out of my
house and taking it home. I sell you חמץ chametz ערב פסח,
erev Pesach, let's go to that example, I know that's going to
culminate in a process or it's the beginning of a process which
is you're going to be eating this over a period of time.
But if I invite you into my home or invite you into
my courtyard which is surrounded by walls, it's רשות היחיד, reshus hayachid,
and sit you down for a meal and offer you food there
or I put the food in front of the dog there, then
the assumption is it's going to be eaten right there. So then
if the dog takes it and takes it out of the courtyard
or the non-Jew takes it and takes it home, that is no
longer my action. The process I began was one about eating in
the courtyard. This is now already a second stage and not my
responsibility.
So the גמרא Gemara says, הא תו למה לי, ha su lama
li, if you had the case of the dog, why did you
need the case of the non-Jew? היינו הך, hainu hach, it's essentially
the same point because it's a non-Jew and your process, as I
said, as opposed to all those other cases, it began a process
which will continue afterward. Here the intention was that it was all
be done in the courtyard. And what happens afterwards is not your
responsibility. So, מהו דתימא, mahu d'seima, I might have thought, האי רמי
עליה והאי לא רמי עליה, hai rami alei vehai lo rami alei,
that you have a responsibility to feed the dog, assuming it's your
pet. You don't have a responsibility to feed the non-Jew. So maybe
one of the reasons we're being lenient is because it is, you
know, you anyway have a responsibility to feed, but maybe we shouldn't
say that by the non-Jew, it's not your responsibility. קא משמע לן
ka mashma lan that that does not matter, that even so, you
are allowed, you're allowed to do this. So, I just want to...
Joseph Mendelowitz if you want the... yeah.
Okay, so now,
so those now are a series of things which, as I said,
if you put them together for בית שמאי, Beit Shammai and you
want to have a comprehensive reason, it could be different reasons: one
could be about שביתת כלים shvisas keilim, and the other about appearances
or something like that, or גזירה, gezeira, you know, if you start
it will lead to something else. But I think it seems to
be strengthening that the consistent theme of בית שמאי Beit Shammai is
beginning a process that then continues on שבת Shabbat. and that you
are involved in, even if it's interestingly a non-Jew who's continuing it.
And again, the real question then becomes, what's the reason for the
exceptions about lighting and so on? Yes.
The Koren has a note that some say we may give food
even to a dog who doesn't belong to us because there's a
specific verse the תורה Torah says we're supposed to give food to
the dogs because they didn't bark at...
okay, all right, very nice. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says
like this: תנו רבנן. Tanu rabbanan:
So, לא ישכיר אדם כליו לנכרי בערב שבת. lo yaskir adam keilav
lenachri be'erev Shabbos. Now we're going on, so we dealt with like
selling them objects, now about renting: don't rent your objects to a
non-Jew ערב שבת. erev Shabbat וברביעי ובחמישי
מותר. u'v'revi'i u'v'chamishi mutar. And on Wednesday, Thursday it's permissible. Excuse me,
again, this is presumably
בית שמאי. Beit Shammai. כיוצא בו, kayotzei vo, similarly...
now,
well actually let's look at תוספות Tosafos before we go on to
this "similarly." If you look at תוספות: Tosafos: לא ישכיר lo yaskir
he says the following: אין לפרש משום שביתת כלים כבית שמאי. ein
lefareish mishum shvisas keilim keBeis Shammai.
Don't say it's about שביתת כלים shvisas keilim. like בית שמאי. Beit
Shammai דאם כן אפילו ברביעי ובחמישי
נמי. de'im kein afilu be'revi'i u've'chamishi nami. It would be prohibited even
on Wednesday and Thursday. So because right, because if you're only משכיר,
maskir, you're only renting and they're still your vessels, so the same
way the הלכה halacha about שביתת בהמה shvisas behema which everybody agrees
is an issue is you can't rent your animal to a non-Jew
if he's going to use it on שבת, Shabbat. you have to
stipulate that he doesn't use it, because it's your animal doing work
on שבת Shabbat, even if it's not under your control right now.
So similarly, says תוספות, Tosafos, it would apply according to בית שמאי
Beit Shammai if בית שמאי Beit Shammai holds of שביתת כלים, shevitat
kelim you couldn't rent him your hoe or your car if he's
going to use it on שבת. Shabbat אלא כבית הלל הוא דלית
להו שביתת כלים. ela keBeis Hillel hu delis lehu shvisas keilim. It's
בית הלל who doesn't have שביתת כלים. shevitat kelim or בחלוק, bekhaluk,
or
כלי kli sometimes means not some type of an instrument to use
but means sometimes garments. So or we're talking about garments, so there's
no שביתת כלים shevitat kelim. wearing a garment, ולא שייך שביתת כלים.
velo shayach shevitat kelim.
So then if all of this is true, that it's not שביתת
כלים shevitat kelim. or it's a garment, why can't you rent it
to them on Friday? So he says, ואסור לפי שנראה כנוטל שכר
שבת ve'assur lefi shenira kenotel sechar Shabbat
because it's like of a totally different concern which you have not
raised here, which doesn't sound like because it's introducing a brand new
concern, which is making money on שבת Shabbat by doing some labor
for somebody. So if I can be a baby sitter for you
on שבת Shabbat, and even if you pay me after שבת, Shabbat?
the problem is is that if all of the money you're paying
me is for work I did on שבת, Shabbat, then I'm earning
money on שבת, Shabbat. that's not a normal type of thing we
think we want people to be doing. That's a problem of שכר
שבת. sechar Shabbat. So the way you get around that is is
that you include in that work done from before שבת. Shabbat.
So if like, a baby sitter coming שבת, Shabbat what work are
you doing before שבת?
Shabbat, Yeah I know, so that's where it's a harder argument. But
somehow, anyway, so maybe if you're putting together snacks to bring to
the kids or something like that. As long as you're מבליע mavlia
it with other payment for שבת, Shabbat. it's okay, but if the
payment is all for work done on שבת, Shabbat. that's a שכר
שבת sechar Shabbat problem. And that's the problem, and right, so those
are issues. Anyway, so that's what תוספות Tosafot says the issue here
is and that's why if you have it a few days before
it includes in it payment for previous days. Although the problem is
as תוספות Tosafot points out then it really should be okay even
if you did it ערב שבת erev Shabbat, because it includes in
it time from before שבת. Shabbat. So it's not so clear that
that's the issue. If you take a look at רש״י, Rashi, רש״י
Rashi says, לא ישכיר כליו lo yaskir kelav the last of the
wide lines, לעשות בהם מלאכה בערב שבת שנראה שמשכיר לו לצורך שבת.
la'asot bahem melacha be'erev Shabbat shenira shemaskir lo letzorech Shabbat.
It's again some type of an appearance sake. If you rent him
the hoe on Friday afternoon, then it looks like you're renting it
to him to use דוקא davka on שבת. Shabbat, But of course
why is that a big deal? He's doing it for himself, he's
not doing it for you. You know? So again it seems like
this could make sense that this is a בית שמאי Beit Shammai
issue. But a בית שמאי Beis Shammai not בית שמאי Beis Shammai
on שביתת כלים. shevitat kelim Because as תוספות Tosafot says it should
be forbidden even on Wednesday, even on Monday. But forget שביתת כלים.
shevitat kelim Remember תוספות Tosafot as I mentioned you pointed out before
that that's just one take on בית שמאי. Beis Shammai More simply
בית שמאי Beis Shammai שביתת כלים shvitat kelim. is not the issue.
So if it's therefore rather an issue of beginning a process and
therefore you can't begin the process of the dough, of the dye,
of the ink, you can't sell him an object that he's going
to carry home because you began that process. So similarly if you
rent him let's say a hoe on Friday afternoon and he winds
up using it on שבת, Shabbat. you also began that process. It's
just like giving him the the items in the home that he's
going to carry home. Okay so that really seems to be the
issue the בית שמאי Beis Shammai's issue. If you did it on
Wednesday or Thursday, then what he does on שבת Shabbat isn't connected
to the beginning of a process you began on Wednesday or Thursday.
That seems to be what's going on here. Yes, Charlie?
Some rabbis and cantors get paid...
Let's not talk about that. But look, if you have to prepare
the ליינינג leining a minute before שבת Shabbat, or whatever, anyway that's
a... but yes, those are issues that need to be addressed. Anyway,
so I would think to read it this way along this line
of בית שמאי Beis Shammai but understand בית שמאי Beis Shammai about
beginning a process. Okay not about שביתת כלים shvitat kelim per se.
I'm sorry, I'm not sure I understood. You're saying if it starts
too close to שבת, Shabbat. it's as if you began a process
that really is meant to start on שבת? Shabbos?
No, not meant to start on שבת, Shabbat but you began a
process which continues throughout שבת. Shabbat. But the question is how long
do you say how do you define what beginning a process means?
If I rent you something and you hoe today and then hoe
tomorrow, by the time you're hoeing on the third day that's already
it's already in your possession by שבת. Shabbat It's not like we
see it as a culmination of something that I began.
So it's some clear demarcation of some point?
No, I mean that's yes it's hard to exactly know, but that
seems to be the difference. Okay so now the גמרא Gemara continues,
כיוצא בו keyotze bo similarly, אין משלחין אגרת ביד נכרי בערב שבת.
en meshalechin igeret beyad nochri be'erev Shabbat.
You can't send a letter. Now this is more obvious than all
the other cases, because here he's doing it for you. You can't
have him to deliver a letter for you if you send it
to him with him on Friday because then it's clear, I mean
even if you didn't explicitly tell him to carry it on שבת
Shabbat. maybe that's implicit or even if he has the option of
skipping שבת, Shabbat. there really much more is he's carrying the letter
for you on שבת. Shabbat Okay so that you can't do. ובארבעה
ובה׳ מותר. u've'arba'a u'veh' mutar. And on Wednesday or Thursday that's okay
because again then already it's not like you're directly sort of something
you began that directly leads into שבת. Shabbat, אמרו עליו על רבי
יוסי הכהן amru alav al Rabbi Yose HaKohen ואמרי לה רבי יוסי
החסיד ve'amre lah Rabbi Yose HaChassid שלא נמצא כתב ידו ביד נכרי
מעולם. shelo nimtza ktav yado beyad nochri me'olam. He never had a
letter of his in the hands of a non-Jew, presumably because even
if you gave it to him a week before he might wind
up carrying it on שבת. Shabbos And here there's something that makes
it more seen as you're involved in the process than the other
cases. Number one is that he's doing it for you as opposed
to selling him the objects in your home or giving him food
or renting him. Here he specifically is doing it for you but
more than that as indicated by the language here כתב ידו, ktav
yado, right? Your handwriting is in his hand so there he's carrying
your letter it also's got your handwriting that really is much more.
like you are part of this process that he's doing. So even
if technically you get out of it once it's a few days
before שבת, Shabbat. but רבי יוסי, Rabbi Yosi, this רבי יוסי Rabbi
Yosi was very stringent, he did not want to do it ever
because
it's like I'm involved in his מלאכה Melacha. on שבת. Shabbos, Yes.
So do we mail a letter on Friday?
Yes, so that's a good question. Do we mail out on Friday?
So this again, this גמרא Gemara, is not as you've seen in
a lot of cases without clearly articulating what the rules are. Okay,
and largely we've been, and there's always the question: are we within
בית שמאי Beis Shammai now or are we within בית הלל? Because
בית שמאי Beit Shammai, is the one that's much more concerned about
beginning a process. So is this issue about the letter and not
doing it on Friday, is that a בית שמאי Beit Shammai. issue
or a בית הלל issue, right? It seems more like a בית
שמאי Beit Shammai issue. Anyway, there are these questions, yes, about how
about sending mail before שבת Shabbat and how to fit this into
general rules we know about אמירה לגוי, amira le-goy, not בית שמאי's
Beit Shammai issues, which as we see are much broader, but you
know a specific thing we all hold of, you can't have a
non-Jew do מלאכה melacha for you on שבת, Shabbat. you know, what
about these types of cases where they have a certain amount of
latitude and so on. So I personally do not put letters in
the mailbox like this just happened the other day like we had
some things we had to mail and it was Friday afternoon and
I could have just dropped them off in the mailbox as I
was walking to שול. shul. But I did not do that, but
it is not clear that it's a problem because nowadays anyway these
people are not working for you, they're working for the postal service,
you know, and your letters just happen to be there amongst a
lot of other letters etc. etc. and they're not obviously mandated, you
know, to do it on שבת. Shabbat? If you'd send something FedEx
next day delivery on Friday, that's a problem. Okay, but anyway, but
there are issues, but they normally get analyzed through the more formalized
rules of אמירה לגוי, amira le-goy, which is not really although it
is what we're dealing with now is a lot about non-Jew, it's
not about אמירה לגוי. amira le-goy. Here it's much more about, seems
to be much more the בית שמאי Beit Shammai sort of, you
know, thrust of beginning a process that ultimately culminates. But this case
of the letter could be a concern of everybody's, אמירה לגוי, amira
le-goy, because he actually he is doing it for you.
Yeah, so usually a מכתב michtav like a letter as opposed to
like an actual manuscript maybe more fearful. Yeah, but we're talking about
a letter, it says איגרת.
igeret. So but still your own personal handwriting, yeah, it's still your
own personal handwriting or maybe that was
more special reason not to let your actual handwriting, yeah, it doesn't
sound like it. You mean כתב יד? ksav yad?
I don't think he means כתב יד ksav yad like we say
כתב יד ksav yad means manuscript. No, it just means handwriting. Yeah,
also can anyone rent something to a non-Jew with specific specifying
not to use it on שבת? Shabbat. That's only for animals because
of שביתת בהמתו, shevisas behemto, okay, but again for non-animals like this,
this is so mostly this
seems like we're in the בית שמאי Beit Shammai, world right now,
although the גמרא Gemara is not being clear about what world it's
in. What's more because, you know, interestingly enough because with mail, you
know, things have changed
now because even let's say you do it at 3:00, will it
make a difference because if their pickup time is 9:30 in the
morning it won't be until 9:30 Sunday? Right, but if you've got
a
problem that is correct, if you've got a problem with it happening
on שבת Shabbat then anytime after the last pickup would be included,
that would be true. But whether it's a problem or not nowadays
is a completely different, I mean it's a different discussion but it's
a large discussion. Okay, תנו רבנן אין משלחין איגרות ביד נכרי ערב
שבת אלא אם כן קצץ לו דמים. Tanu Rabbanan ein meshalchin igros
beyad nachri erev shabbos ela im kein katzatz lo damim. You can
only send it to them if you've been קוצץ דמים, kotzetz damim,
set a fixed price. Now this is important to know and it
goes back to the משנה Mishnah I want to mention something about
the משנה Mishnah earlier because interestingly the גמרא Gemara doesn't discuss it
so much. But, you know, the משנה Mishnah talks about dropping off
the clothes to the non-Jew and all those types of things and
בית שמאי Beit Shammai says they have to have time to finish
it and בית הלל says no, even if you drop it off
a minute before שבת. Shabbat Now why is that? I mean if
you drop it off a minute before שבת Shabbat. then he's working
for you on שבת. Shabbat. So basically what's not explicit in the
משנה Mishnah, but gets clarified elsewhere is that
there's with two criteria. Number one is you're not paying him by
the hour, you're paying him a fixed fee. Okay, and number two
is that he has the ability to do it sometime other than
שבת. Shabbat. If you dropped it off to him a minute before
שבת Shabbat and you said I'm picking it up, you know, ten
minutes after שקיעה shkia or ten minutes after צאת tzeis and there
was no time he could have done it not שבת, Shabbat then
that's not good even if you're paying him a fixed fee. You
have to leave time. Now the question what theoretically means he has
time to do it is always an interesting question. Like sometimes I'll,
you know, you drop your car off at the mechanic and say
be ready Saturday morning. You drop it off Friday and he says
that's okay, I'm not going to be here till Sunday. Okay, but
I'm telling you Saturday morning, it's very fine but I'm not going
to be till Sunday, I'm not, you can get it done Sunday
for all I can care. So okay fine, that's like one case
where he's telling me but I'm saying I don't need that done.
But let's say I need it Saturday night, I'm driving to the
airport, whatever, I need it Saturday night and I drop it off
to him on, you know,
so well I'm trying to think of a better scenario.
Say like two hours after שבת Shabbat. and you drop it off
a minute before שבת.
Shabbat Right, two hours after שבת, Shabbat so you know he's closed
at five. Right, right, that's the issue. The issue is what if
he's closed, meaning let's say you drop it off, yeah that's the
issue. You drop it off a minute before שבת Shabbat? and he's
closed Saturday night and you're going to pick it up first thing
Sunday morning. So in practice the only time he has time to
fix it is over שבת. Shabbat, But in theory, but you know
in theory he could, if he wanted to, he could, you know,
rearrange his day and open up his garage on Saturday night and
do it Saturday night. I'm not stopping him. So that raises an
interesting... What does it mean he could do it not on שבת?
Shabbat. How much theoretical is the could? But that's the basic principles
that you can have a non-Jew do מלאכה, give something to them,
step number one: it's a fee for the job, not by the
hour. Number two: it's the ability to do it not on שבת.
Shabbat, Now, why can it not be a fee for the hour?
Because if you pay him hourly, then even if he could have
worked Saturday night or Sunday, if he is working שבת Shabbat, and
you are paying him for that hour of work, not for the
job, but for that actual hour of work, and that was a
שבת Shabbat. hour of work, then it's essentially like you are having
him work for you on שבת. Shabbat, So that's why you need
קצץ דמים katzatz damim and the ability to do it not on
שבת. Shabbat Now, before we continue in the גמרא, Gemara I just
want to mention one other thing which תוספות Tosafot mentioned earlier, but
I'll bring it in now because it's relevant, is there's a discussion
about whether this applies to construction work, to work on your property.
Because it could be work on your property is much more public
and everybody knows, oh yeah, they're putting up Lentzer's house over there,
and then they see the people working on the property on שבת.
Shabbat. So even if it is that even if they're able to
do it on Sunday, and sometimes actually they're not, if they got
a deadline and it costs money for them overhead, but even if
in theory they could do it another time and even though you're
paying them, even if you're paying them for the job and not
for the hour, and very often you are paying them for the
hour at least at the worker level, nevertheless, that raises issues because
it looks very much like they're doing work for you on שבת
Shabbat, in your on your property. So there's discussions whether that's always
true, and nowadays, it is a big issue because if you have
people doing construction for you, sometimes you pay the foreman and you
pay the whole job and the foreman then pays the workers by
the hour. Anyway, those are big issues, so תוספות Tosafot has a
discussion about this, so I just want to just read you if
we just jump back for a second on י״ח עמוד א׳, Yod
Chet Amud Aleph,
the very four lines of תוספות. Tosafot. תוספות Tosafot says that רבינו
תם Rabbeinu Tam said you could even do it on like on
on land, on property, and have them build for you assuming that
the basic criteria were met: that they could in theory do it
not on שבת Shabbat? and you're paying them for the whole job.
But then he says, although רבינו תם Rabbeinu Tam said it was
מותר, mutar, it says the last line of this תוספות Tosafot before
the words get small, of the wide lines on the top of
י״ח עמוד א׳, Yod Chet Amud Aleph, the top, very top, he
says דפירש רבינו תם נמי כשבנה את ביתו לא סמך על תשובתו
ולא רצה להתיר. d’peirash Rabbeinu Tam nami k’she’banah et beito lo samach
al teshuvato v’lo ratzah l’hatir. So even though he said that in
theory you could do it when it comes to constructing a house,
for his own personal house, he was more מחמיר. machmir. So there
are all these הלכות halachos about whether these things there are greater
limitations when it comes to building on property. Yes, Charlie.
This would seem to get us out of the letter, the letter
problem because the price of a first-class letter is fixed.
Oh, that's a good point. Right. And in theory, they right and
they could do it. I mean, again, that's a question about in
theory they could do it not on שבת. Shabbat. If the job
is to, you know, if the job is to pick up the
mail and that's the job for this שבת Shabbat. and you put
it in, even though in theory they
and they pick up on שבת Shabbat. and not Sunday for their
convenience.
Right, right. So yes, there's definitely a lot of mechanic jobs that
are good ones because they also charge you a labor rate. Oh,
that's true.
Because they do, they charge
you, you know, part of it is labor,
like they break it out.
Monday
through Friday they charge by the
hour.
So that means you can't do it.
Yeah,
that's a good
question about that, about the fact that you wind up paying by
the hour. What if they do it on שבת?
Shabbat, If part of it is parts and the other is labor.
You've got almost anything unless it's like an inspection,
which
is totally fixed price sometimes. Yeah.
The question is how much if they really have a lot of
latitude. You're right. I have to look about I have to double
check about those two criteria working together. Like if they really have
a lot of latitude, then how much, you know, even if you're
paying per hour, they could have done it not on שבת, Shabbat,
although the reality is
so it may not be true. Yeah, I don't think we can
stop the question which is: you're not paying the person, you're paying
the corporation.
Oh, right. That nowadays, certainly that's true. You mean like in the
mechanic example?
When mechanics you are paying the person.
Yeah, alright, so with the mechanic, if it's a if the guy
owns his own shop, you know, so he's incorporated like... I don't
really know if that makes so much of a difference. But you
know, you're not paying the postal carrier, you're paying, you know, the
United States Postal Service.
Right, right. And that does raise very important right הלכה halacha about
who are they doing it for? Maybe they're doing it for their
company. They're not doing it for you in particular. And there are
definitely those that want to say that a lot of those parameters
change nowadays because of those
realities.
Yes, Avram? What? I've Sears insurance and my garage door doesn't work.
I call them up. He said he can come in two weeks,
but on Saturday.
Only on Saturday he
is available.
Right. So that raises the other definitely raises הלכה... halacha... exactly those
things raise הלכה halacha questions if they come and send somebody, yeah.
If you just a brief comment with respect
to מראית העין, marit ha'ayin, the
the case where someone is carrying a letter, even though it's his
handwriting, that would seem to have to be the most, you know,
least obtrusive because you know, some a non-Jew is walking in the
street, how do you know it's Lentzer's?
Right. Right, right, if it's a question about appearances, right. If it's
about this issue about like you participating in a process then it
could be even if it's right. Okay, so let's keep on going.
So it says like this. אין משלחין איגרות ביד עובד כוכבים בערב
שבת Shabbat אלא אם כן קצץ לו דמים *Ein mshalchin igros biyad
oved kochavim berev Shabbos ela im kein katzatz lo damim* unless you
have a fixed price. בית שמאי Beit Shammai אומרים כדי שיגיע לביתו
*Beis Shammai omrim kedei sheyagiya lveiso* and he needs time just like
when you sell him an object, he needs time to get home.
ובית הלל אומרים כדי שיגיע לבית הסמוך לחומה *Uveis Hillel omrim kedei
sheyagiya levayis hasamuch lechoma*. He has to get to the house at
the edge of the next city.
So just like the דף *daf* before though was like really out
of your...
well according to Rabbi Akiva. Anyway, so this is about sending a
letter. Okay, so here it sounds like Beis Hillel agrees that there's
concerns about sending a letter, but fine if you didn't set a
fixed price, we understand why there are concerns because then it's like
he's doing... you're hiring him to do מלאכה *melakha* for you on
Shabbat. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says like this.
ולא קצץ *Vlo katzatz*.
So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says exactly that. How do you read
this requirement that he gets to the next city? Both you have
to have a fixed price and he has to get to the
next city, or either a fixed price or if you didn't fix
the price and it's an hourly thing, then he has to get
to the next city. So that's what the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* seems
to say. ולא קצץ *Vlo katzatz*, why you have to get to
the next city already? You should have a fixed price. So אמר
רב Rav ששת הכי קאמר *Amar Rav Sheshes hachi kaamar*. ואם לא
קצץ *Vim lo katzatz*, if you didn't fix the price then and
you're paying him by the hour, then בית שמאי Beit Shammai. אומרים
עד שיגיע לביתו בית הלל אומרים עד שיגיע לבית הסמוך לחומה *Beis
Shammai omrim ad sheyagiya lveiso Beis Hillel omrim ad sheyagiya levayis hasamuch
lechoma*. That's when you have to have the chance to get out
to get to the house that he's going to or get to
the next city. So here it actually seems like,
right. So anyway, so here we see that if you fixed the
price, you don't have to worry so much because then he's doing
it on his own חשבון *cheshbon*, but if you didn't fix the
price and you're paying him hourly, then he has to get done
with it or have the ability to get done with it before
Shabbat. Now the גמרא Gemara. *Gemara* says like this, ואמרת רישא אין
משלחין *Veamarta reisha ein mshalchin*, which is a little hard to understand
what exactly the question is, but anyway somehow the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*
is bothered, some have a different גרסא *girsa* that says but don't
we have a תוספתא Tosefta *Tosefta* that says אין משלחין *ein mshalchin*,
presumably even if you... even if he could get to the next
city. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says לא קשיא *lo kashya*. הא
דקביעי דואר במתא הא דלא קביעי דואר במתא *Ha dkviei doar bmasa
ha dla kviei doar bmasa*. One is whether there is a basically
a post office in the city and the other is that there's
not a post office in the city. Why does that matter? So
the way רש"י Rashi *Rashi* explains and again the פוסקים *poskim* have
like go through a lot of effort to try to understand how
this fits into general principles about אמירה לעכו"ם *amira lakum*, but basically
even if he gets to the next city, right, he has to
go throughout the whole city finding out where שמואל Shmuel *Shmuel* lives,
you know, and then he's going to wind up still carrying the
letter for you on Shabbat even if he's in the next city.
But if there's a post office, all he has to do is
just get it to the postal... you know, to the central post
office in the next city and then everybody will come, you know,
to pick to check up for their mail in that place. So
here even if it's a case of ולא קצץ *vlo katzatz*, the
way this is being read is it's not enough that he has
time to get to the next city. That's only enough if there's
a... if there's a basically a post office. But if there's no
post office, he needs more time. He needs time to find the
guy and to actually deliver. Okay, so that's about again, that's about
mail and we see here that it is also a concern about
Beis Hillel here explicitly, but partly it's because here you're actually paying
him to do something for
you and he winds up doing it on Shabbat.
And that wouldn't necessarily apply today because today I mean the letter
carrier's going to go to your apartment, so they're still going to,
you
know, need to know where's where's... Right. Right. So like I said,
today today the issues are different. תנו רבנן אין מפליגין בספינה פחות
מג' ימים קודם לשבת *Tanu rabanan ein mafligin bisefina pachos migimmel yamim
kodem leShabbos*. You cannot set out for a cruise, right, on a
boat, three days before Shabbat. Okay. Now that's three days. Until now
it had been Wednesday and Thursday was okay. Here even three days
is no good. Okay, now why is that different? Well let's see
until the end. במה דברים אמורים לדבר הרשות *Bameh devarim amurim ledvar
harashus*. That's if you're going just for like, you know, discretionary. אבל
לדבר מצוה *Aval ledvar mitzvah*, שפיר דמי *shapir dami*, then it's okay.
ופוסק עמו על מנת לשבות ואינו שובת דברי רבי *Ufosek imo al
mnas lishbos veino shoveis divrei Rabbi*. And so Rabbi says though what
you have to do is you have to stipulate with the captain
that he's not going to, you know, sort of sail on Shabbat.
He's not going to run his ship on Shabbat. But then, you
know, the captain doesn't really have to do it. Meaning it's called
with a wink and a nod. Okay. Yes, I'm paying you but,
you know, please don't go on Shabbat. Sure, sure, sure, whatever you
say. Okay. Anyway, so that's what Rabbi says. ורבן גמליאל אומר אינו
צריך *VRabban Gamliel omer eino tzarich*. You don't have to make that
stipulation. ומצור לצידן אפילו בערב שבת afilu b'erev Shabbat, מותר muttar *UmiTzor
lTzidan afilu berev Shabbos mutar*. On Friday you can go from Tzor
to Tzidan which was a short trip and that they would often
do that travel because there would be a market on ערב שבת
erev Shabbat *erev Shabbos*, so that is permissible. But a larger trip
not. So what's the issue here? Now if he's if he's basically
it's your private yacht and he's doing it just for you, then
it would seem everybody would agree you have to stipulate and you
couldn't even do it with a wink and a nod. How can
he be, you know, driving your ship for you on Shabbat? But
the point seems to be obviously that you're not the only person.
It's not a private yacht. There's a lot of other people. So
therefore how much is he really, you know, doing it for you?
He's doing it like a convenience, it's his job, he's doing it
on Shabbat and so on. How much responsibility do you really need
to take to make to ask him not to do it on
Shabbat? That seems to be to some degree the debate of Rabbi
and Rabban Gamliel. What's the idea of three days? Why does it
have to worry about three days before and so on? So, you
know, it could you could try to fit this into some
of the... as opposed to something like renting something or other processes
which are seen
as only if they begin ערב שבת erev Shabbat are they seen
as somehow continuing into שבת. Shabbat You know, a trip that's going,
a transatlantic voyage, obviously it's a process that does begin, that does
go on many, many days, and if you do it at least
three days within שבת, Shabbat. which is considered to be the time
connected to שבת, Shabbat then you have begun a process where now
you are traveling on שבת. Shabbat, It's not like you find yourself
on a boat and it happens to be going; no, it's all
a process that you began. So one way to understand it is
along the lines of what we sort of said before about there's
a longer amount of time before you have to worry because the
process is fundamentally a much more ongoing process. But there's a lot
of other reasons given by the ראשונים. Rishonim. One has to do
with basically a simple issue of עונג שבת, Oneg Shabbat, that you'll
have seasick, you'll be seasick and therefore you need three days in
order to get acclimated to the sea. You know, there's other concerns
about maybe you'll get yourself in a מקום סכנה makom sakanah and
that'll lead to having to be מחלל שבת, mechalel Shabbat, but again,
and the idea of three days becomes important because then if it
really is an issue like I said about beginning a process or
it's an issue about like you'll have to be מחלל שבת mechalel
Shabbat because it'll be מקום סכנה, makom sakanah, and even though obviously
once it's a מקום סכנה makom sakanah you're allowed to and obligated
to be מחלל שבת, mechalel Shabbat, you don't want to create those
scenarios. So those explanations, why then is it limited to three days?
This gets to the idea that more than three days before שבת,
Shabbat you don't have to be thinking about שבת Shabbat. yet. It's
not connected conceptually to the following שבת. Shabbat So only Wednesday, by
Tuesday already that's שייך shayach to the previous שבת, Shabbat and therefore
you can do something now and you don't have to worry, oh
my gosh, if I go on the trip on Tuesday what's going
to happen on שבת? Shabbat If you're more than three days out,
you're not responsible to be considering the implications for the following שבת.
Shabbat And if it's the seasickness explanation, then it's just an idea
that it takes a couple of days to get used to the
sea.
But what if you know that you don't get seasick at all
and it wouldn't be a problem for you then, right? Or what
if it takes you longer, then you couldn't do it on Tuesday
either.
In theory, in theory, yep.
תנו רבנן: there's an
exemption so that's built into the this is obviously just a דרבנן,
d'rabbanan, right? What exemption? דבר מצוה. d'var mitzvah. Ah, yeah.
So that's a good point too, why we're not מקפיד makpid on
the דבר מצוה d'var mitzvah aspect, so also shows that this is
at some degree דרבנן, d'rabbanan that's correct. Okay,
or that whatever the concern is, right, it's overridden by the דבר
מצוה. d'var mitzvah. רבן שמעון בן גמליאל: Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel: נוהגים
היו, nohagim hayu, so I'm sorry, skipped one. תנו רבנן: אין צרין
על עיירות של נכרים פחות מג' ימים קודם לשבת. Ein sarrin al
ayarot shel nochrim pachos migimmel yamim kodem l'Shabbat. You cannot sort of
lay siege to a city that you're doing war against. I don't
know when
this הלכתא דמשיחא hilchata d'Meshicha unless we're talking about the time of
the חשמונאים. Chashmonaim. Anyway, you can't lay siege to a city
less than three days before שבת. Shabbat? Again, because once you're involved
in the siege, it'll lead to חילול שבת, chillul Shabbat, which might
be מותר muttar, once you're in war, but this actually works very
well explaining the חילול שבת chillul Shabbat concern by the boat. Yes,
if you're in war you can be מחלל שבת; mechalel Shabbat; yes,
if it's סכנה sakanah you'll be מחלל שבת. mechalel Shabbat. But don't
set it up so that that's the situation you're going to be
in. So don't go to get on a boat three days before,
don't start a siege three days before. Okay, however, ואם
התחילו אין מפסיקין. v'im hitchilu ein mafsikin. Once you begin, then you
don't interrupt, then you continue it throughout שבת. Shabbat. וכן היה שמאי
אומר: v'chen hayah Shammai omer: עד רדתה. ad ridetah. It speaks about
כי תצור אל עיר ימים רבים, ki tatzur el ir yamim rabbim,
many days, until it comes down, אפילו בשבת. afilu b'Shabbat. So the
same way you obviously naturally because war is always related to סכנת
נפשות sakanas nefashos issues. Okay, so it seems to read that's nice
to read that in parallel to the boat case. רבן שמעון בן
גמליאל, Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel, back to the משנה: Mishnah נוהגים היו,
nohagim hayu, we used to give our white garments to the launderer.
It seems to be following בית שמאי, Beit Shammai although he was
part of the בית הלל, but he seems to be מחמיר machmir
on himself like בית שמאי. Beit Shammai And not only did we
give them clothes like a couple of hours before שבת, Shabbat. but
the white clothes we made sure to give three days before שבת,
Shabbat so there'd be plenty of time to do it. תניא, Tanya,
אמר רבי צדוק: amar Rabbi Tzadok: כך היה מנהגו של רבן גמליאל,
kach hayah minhago shel Rabban Gamliel, this was the approach of the
house of רבן גמליאל, Rabban Gamliel, שהיו נותנין כלי לבן לכובס ג'
ימים קודם לשבת, shehayu notnin klei lavan l'koves gimmel yamim kodem l'Shabbat,
they would give white garments three days before שבת Shabbat to the
launderer, וצבעונים, u'tzvivonim, and colored garments, אפילו בערב שבת, Shabbat because that
somehow took less time. ומדבריהם למדנו, u'midvreihem lamadnu, and from this we
understand, we can learn, שהלבנים קשים לכבסן יותר מן הצבעונים. shehalvanim kashim
l'chabsan yoter min hatzvivonim. I understand. So implicitly it takes more time
to clean white clothes than it does to clean colored clothes. As
we say, if you don't have bleach, I don't know when bleach
was sort of discovered or whatever, figured out to use that for
cleaning, but anyway, 18th century. Oh, really? 18th century. Okay, so if
you don't have bleach, it's a lot harder to get clothes to
look white again than it is for colored garments. So anyway, the
גמרא Gemara says like this: אביי
הוה יהיב ליה לההוא מנא דצביעה לקצרא. Abaye havah yahiv lei l'hahu
mana d'tzviya l'katzara. אביי Abaye gave a certain colored garment to a
קצרא, katzara, which is a launderer. אמר ליה: Amar lei: כמה בעית
עלויה? kama ba'it aluwei? How much is this going to cost me?
אמר ליה: Amar lei: כדי לבן. k'dei lavan. It costs the same
as white garments. אמר ליה: Amar lei: קרקדבך רבנן סרטי, karkadvach rabbanan
sartai, Rabbis already beat you to it. I learned from this תוספתא
that white garments is more effort than colored garments, so I expect
you to give me a lesser price for my colored garment than
for my white garment. garments. In terms of you to launder it.
Okay, so you really had no idea.
Yeah. אמר אביי. Amar Abbaye. אמר אביי, Amar Abbaye, I know. אמר
אביי, Amar Abbaye, האי מאן דיהיב מני לקצרא במשחא, Hai man deyahiv
manei l'kitsra bimishkha, if you are giving a garment to a launderer,
במשחא נסיב ליה ובמשחא נישקול מיניה, bimishkha neseiv leh ubimishkha nishkul mineh,
measure it before you give it to him and measure it when
you take it back from him. Why? דאי טפי, De'itfei, if it's
larger than the size when you gave it to him, אחסא דמתחיה,
akhsa dematchaya, then he stretched it and he made it, he damaged
it by overstretching it. ואי בציר, Ve'ibatsir, and if it's shorter than
you gave it to him, אחסא דכווציה, akhsa dechavtsia, then he damaged
it by shrinking it. So if you make sure that you're getting
your money's worth and that the guy is competent when you give
stuff to the cleaners. Okay. ובשוין אלו ואלו שטוענין. Uveshavin elu ve'elu
sheto'anin. Now they both agree, even though בית שמאי Beit Shammai does
not allow these processes to begin, that you can put on a
beam ערב שבת Erev Shabbat. to get the oil out of the
olives or the juice out of the grapes. So we're going to
see why that is. I should say the תוספתא is actually quite
interesting, right? Because there's cases that everybody agrees is a problem like
the roasting of the meat and of the egg. We quoted it
yesterday. It's going to be a משנה Mishnah. coming up. Even בית
הלל says that's a problem, we explained because you'll stir the coals.
There's a case that everybody agrees is okay, which is putting of
this beam on the olives and on the grapes. And even בית
שמאי Beit Shammai says it's okay. It's not clear why those are
agreed upon. Anyway, in the תוספתא it's very interesting because בית שמאי
Beis Shammai says you can't do any process before שבת Shabbat and
בית הלל says it's okay. So then like בית הלל says to
בית שמאי, Beis Shammai well how is that different than the beam
on the olives? You say that's okay, why do you say everything
else is a problem? And then בית שמאי Beis Shammai says back
to בית הלל, well how is it different than roasting the egg
and roasting the meat, which you say isn't good? So everything else
also should be not good. So what's fascinating about that is that
it's clear that there were these two rulings that were very ancient
rulings that predated בית שמאי Beis Shammai and בית הלל, that you
can have the beam on the olives, that you can do, and
that you can't roast the meat and the egg right before שבת.
Shabbat? And the question was which one is the exception and which
one is the rule. Can you begin a process before שבת Shabbat?
or not? And that's the debate of בית הלל בית שמאי. But
again what's fascinating is that it's a debate based on the fact
that there were two rulings without a general rule being articulated and
they were debating which one to take their lead from. So here
is the case that everybody agrees is okay, which is the beam.
So the גמרא Gemara says מאי שנא כולהו דגזרו בהו בית שמאי?
maishana kulu degazu bei Beit Shammai? Why by all the others did
בית שמאי make a גזירה? gzeira? And תוספות Tosafot points out that
here notice it says גזירה, gzeira, it doesn't say שביתת כלים. shvitat
kelim, So שביתת כלים keilim was a very extreme and difficult position.
Here we're just saying don't begin a process
ערב שבת, Erev Shabbat, גזירה, gzeira, it's continuing on שבת, Shabbat it'll
lead to being מחלל שבת. m'chalel Shabbat. So why by the other
cases did they make a גזירה gzeira by starting those processes? ומאי
שנא קורות בית הבד ועיגולי הגת? Umaishana korot beit habad ve'igulei hagat?
And why when it comes to olives and
grapes that they did not make a גזירה? gzeira? So גמרא Gemara
says הנהו hannah because all the other
cases דאי עביד להו בשבת de'avid lehu beShabbat איכא למיחייב חטאת, itzal
mechayev chatat, you'd be, it would be a real violation of שבת
Shabbat, you'd have to bring a חטאת. chatat. So therefore גזרו בהו
בית שמאי ערב שבת עם חשיכה. gazru bei Beit Shammai erev Shabbat
im chasheicha. They didn't let you do it ערב שבת Erev Shabbat
right before it got dark. They didn't let you. It had to
have time to basically complete or mostly complete before שבת. Shabbat, קורות
בית הבד ועיגולי הגת, Korot beit habad ve'igulei hagat, these cases about
the beams, אי עביד
בשבת לא מחייב חטאת, ya'avid beShabbat lo mechayev chatat, even if you
put the beams on the olives on שבת Shabbat. you would not
be חייב חטאת. chayav chatat. לא גזרו, Lo gazru, they were not
גוזר. gozer. Now why would you not be חייב חטאת? chayav chatat?
You're squeezing out juice from olives and grapes, it's a classic איסור
issur of סחיטה. s'chita. Why not? So the גמרא Gemara will deal
with this. But again I want before we get to that answer,
I want you to note that here it's saying the reason of
בית שמאי is not because of שביתת כלים, it's because of a
גזירה. gzeira. And the גזירה gzeira is either that maybe you'll start
fiddling with it on שבת Shabbat. like מחתה בגחלים machta begachalim and
you'll do a מלאכה on שבת Shabbat, because you're fiddling with it,
or because next time around you'll say, heck, if the ink and
the dye could be happening on שבת Shabbat even though I started
it a minute before שקיעה, shkia, what's the big difference starting it
a minute before שקיעה shkia or starting it on שבת? Shabbat I'm
allowed to do the dyeing on שבת. Shabbat. And next time it'll
come for you actually to begin it on שבת. Shabbat So that's
בית שמאי's concern that we don't want you to start a process
beforehand that would be a מלאכה דאורייתא melacha de'orayta were you to
do it on שבת Shabbat itself. Now we have to ask why
are the case of the olives and grapes different? So let's take
a look. So the גמרא Gemara says אמר רבי יוסי ברבי, Amar
Rabbi Yose bar Rabbi, so it says, I'm sorry, מאן תנא דכל
מידי דאתי ממילא שפיר דמי? Man tanna dechol midi de'ati mimmela shapir
dami? Who's the one that says that anything that would happen by
itself, meaning the understanding is that before you put the grapes and
the olive into these sort of pressing vats you would first crush
them. By the olives you might stamp on them, the grapes you
might stamp on them, by the olives you might sort of have
them in a mill, but you would crush them first and then
you would put them in these vats and put the heavy weight
on it and it would all of it would come out. So
the גמרא is going to understand that the reason it's not דאורייתא
de'orayta even if you were to do it on שבת Shabbat and
the reason בית שמאי therefore could be okay with it starting ערב
שבת Erev Shabbat, is because once you've already crushed them, the juices
will come out anyway. So sort of encouraging them to come out
a little bit faster
It's a good question. Yeah, I mean it's a good question, you
know. Let's take a look at the גמרא. So it says like
this. אמר תו... Amar To... So who is the one that says
that if it's going to happen by itself, it's not a problem,
it's not a מלאכה דאורייתא? melacha De'oraita? So
אמר רבי יוסי ברבי חנינא, Amar Rabbi Yose be-Rabbi Chanina, רבי ישמעאל
Rabbi Yishmael היא, hi, דתנן de-tenan השום והבוסר והמלילות. hashum ve-haboser ve-hamalilot.
If you have garlic or בוסר boser unripe grapes and מלילות malilot
which are like unripe stalks of wheat, שריסקן מבעוד יום sheriskan mibe'od
yom and you crushed them ערב שבת. Erev Shabbat. So as long
as you crushed it ערב שבת, Erev Shabbat, now the juices will
come out by themselves or in theory could. רבי ישמעאל אומר יגמור
משתחשך ורבי עקיבא אומר לא יגמור. Rabbi Yishmael omer yigmor mishetichshach ve-Rabbi
Akiva omer lo yigmor. You can finish it once it gets dark,
and Rabbi Akiva says you can't. Now what does it mean finish
it? So the simple sense might be it's even לכתחילה lechatchila to
do. So תוספות Tosafot discusses that as a possibility. Now squeezing out
juices is really primarily only a problem from grapes and olives. Here
at least two of the three were not grapes and olives, but
there was a case of unripe grapes. So anyway תוספות Tosafot raises
the possibility that if you really ground them very, very well, maybe
even לכתחילה lechatchila you can finish it up on שבת Shabbat, because
the stuff is going to come out easily by itself. Another possibility
of what יגמור yigmor means is that you're allowed to eat from
the stuff that the juices that come out. It's not considered נולד,
nolad, you're allowed to eat from it and so on. And that
is then an evidence, the fact that you're allowed to eat from
it becomes an evidence that it could not have been, it could
not be that their further squeezing out would have been a מלאכה
דאורייתא melacha De'oraita to do directly, because then we would have given
a more strict ruling about the juices that did come out. We
wouldn't want you to eat the juices, because if you eat the
juices, you'll come to squeeze it directly. So the fact that we're
letting you eat the juices, drink the juices, proves that even were
you to squeeze it directly, it would not be חילול שבת. chillul
Shabbat. That's how תוספות Tosafot understands. So here you see once it's
already crushed and will come out by itself, even were you to
do it yourself, it would not be חילול שבת. chillul Shabbat. רבי
אליעזר אומר, Rabbi Eliezer omer, Rabbi Eliezer says, רב אלעזר הוא. Rav
Elazar hu. So Rabbi Eliezer says it's Rabbi Elazar. Okay. ורבי אמי
אמר ve-Rabbi Ami amar Rabbi Elazar says it's Rabbi Elazar the Tanna.
דתנן במתני' de-tenan be-matnitin חלות דבש שריסקן מבעוד יום challot devash sheriskan
mibe'od yom if you have these literally loaves of honey, things that
you took from the beehive, that you crushed them ערב שבת Erev
Shabbat and ויצאו מעצמן ve-yatzu me-atzman and then the honey ran off
on its own, אסור. assur. Now here you don't have any beam
on it or anything, it's just the juices are running out, so
you can't drink the juices. Why can't the honey? Why? Because either
as I said it is either a נולד nolad issue, or because
it is a case that we're concerned that you'll come to do
it, and if we let you drink the honey you'll come to
finish the process on your own.
רבי אלעזר מתיר. Rabbi Elazar mattir. Rabbi Elazar says it's permissible. So
you see if Rabbi Elazar says this permissible, the inference is it
cannot have been a מלאכה to do it on your own. Once
it was crushed ערב שבת, Shabbat. he says even if were you
to do it directly, it would not be a מלאכה, and therefore
he's going to allow you to benefit from the juices that run
off. רבי יוסי ברבי חנינא מאי טעמא לא אמר כרבי אלעזר? Rabbi
Yose be-Rabbi Chanina mai ta'ama lo amar ke-Rabbi Elazar? Why did you
not say like Rabbi Eliezer that said this case about the honey?
That's a pretty good example that implicit in that is that it's
not a biblical שבת Shabbat problem. אמר לך, amar lach, he would
say, התם הוא דמעיקרא אוכלא ולבסוף אוכלא. hatam hu di-me'ikara ochla u-lesof
ochla. No, because honey is a type of a food. And therefore
הכא מעיקרא אוכלא והשתא משקא. hacha me-ikara ochla ve-hashta mashka. Here it
starts as food like a grape and it ends with a liquid
which is juices. Now why does that differ? A, could be a
difference because of נולד, nolad, how much is this considered something new?
But again the נולד nolad issue doesn't seem directly relevant to our
question of whether it's a biblical problem to squeeze it or not.
So the other issue seems to be, right, can you squeeze lemons
into your water on שבת? Shabbat Into your tea on שבת? Shabbat,
Yes or no? Good question. No, you cannot squeeze. How can... if
you want lemon in your tea on שבת Shabbat what do you
do?
You put
in sugar and then you mix the sugar in the tea. Or
you can squeeze a lemon onto your fish or onto your salad
on שבת, Shabbat. but you can't squeeze it straight into a cup.
The prohibition of squeezing to produce the juices is only if it
culminates in a juice. If it culminates in a food, if it
gets into the sugar or onto the salad or onto the fish,
then it actually is not a prohibition of squeeze. So therefore he
says don't bring me any proofs from the honey. There it culminates,
even though honey is obviously a liquid in terms of its consistency,
הלכתית halachit it's a food, and therefore it would not have been...
also you could say it's not like a normal case of squeezing,
it's not like the stuff is absorbed inside and then you are
squeezing it out, you know, the honey it's merely, the honey is
just like there, it's just interspersed with the wax or whatever. Anyway,
so he says that to me is not a proof. Starts as
food ends as food. If you want a proof that it's מותר,
mutar you have to get the harder case, the case of ending
with liquid. Okay. So now the גמרא says like this. אמר רבי
אלעזר אמר לך, Amar Rabbi Elazar amar lach, הא שמיע ליה לרבי
אלעזר ha shami'a lei le-Rabbi Elazar דאפילו בזיתים וענבים
נמי שרי. de-afillu be-zeitim va-anavim nami sharei. I have a ברייתא braita
that I know that Rabbi Elazar doesn't only allow the honey case,
he even allows the olives and the grapes cases. דהכי אתא רב
הושעיא מנהרדעא אתא ואייתי
מתניתא
בידיה. de-hachi ata Rav Hoshaia mi-Nahardea ata ve-aytei matnita beyadeih. He came
and he brought a ברייתא braita in his hands. He learned a
ברייתא braita? in נהרדעא. Nahardea. What's the ברייתא? Baraita, זיתים וענבים שריסקן
מערב
שבת. zeitim va-anavim sheriskan me-erev Shabbat. Same case except here with olives
and grapes. You crushed them ערב שבת. Shabbat, ויצאו מעצמן VeYatzu MeAtzman
and then the juices ran off on שבת, Shabbat. אסורין, Assurin, it's
forbidden to use the juices because you'll come to squeeze them directly
and presumably that would be a מלאכה. רבי אלעזר, Rabbi Elazar, רבי
שמעון, Rabbi Shimon, מתירים. Mattirim. Rabbi Elazar and Rabbi Shimon say it's
okay, you can have the juices, we're not afraid you'll squeeze it
because even if you would squeeze it, it would not be a
חילול שבת. Chillul Shabbat. רבי יוסי ברבי חנינא ברייתא לא שמיע ליה.
Rabbi Yose bar Rabbi Chanina baraita lo shemi'a lei. And the reason
Rabbi Yose bar Rabbi Chanina did not go by this Rabbi Elazar
is he didn't know the ברייתא, Baraita and therefore he quoted the
position about רבי יוסי Rabbi Yose who was about... excuse me, about
רבן גמליאל, Rabban Gamliel, רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael who is very explicit
about the case about the, you know, what do you call it,
the about the garlic and so on, that there you can benefit
from the juices that run off. So now the גמרא says, רבי
יוסי בר... so the גמרא says, רבי אלעזר מאי טעמא לא אמר
כרבי יוסי בר חנינא? Rabbi Elazar mai ta'ama lo amar ke'Rabbi Yose
bar Chanina? So Rabbi Elazar who went by this רבי אליעזר, Rabbi
Eliezer, the ברייתא about the grapes and olives, what about why did
he not like the משנה
that
Rabbi Yose bar Chanina quoted? The משנה that has רבי ישמעאל Rabbi
Yishmael being lenient by juices that come off. אמר רבי יוחנן במחוסרין
דיכה, Amar Rabbi Yochanan be'mechusrin dikah, here's why. I'm sorry, I skipped
a line there. למה כרבי יוסי בר חנינא? Lama ke'Rabbi Yose bar
Chanina? אמר לך לאו איתמר עלה? Amar lach lav itmar alah? No,
because we have the following qualification. אמר אבא ברבי חנינא אמר רבי
יוחנן במחוסרין דיכה כולי עלמא לא פליגי. Amar Abba bar Rabbi Chanina
amar Rabbi Yochanan be'mechusrin dikah kulei alma lo pligi. If things have
not been crushed already, then nobody argues. Of course you can't squeeze
it on שבת. Of course it's a מלאכה דאורייתא, Melacha D'Oraisa, that
squeezing out juices from olives and grapes. So nobody would ever be
talking that it hasn't already been crushed. That clearly is אסור. Assur.
כי פליגי, Ki pligi, when do they argue? במחוסרין שחיקה, be'mechusrin shechika,
that they have not been, or
should I say, ורש"י ve'Rashi says סחיטה, sechita, whatever, which is, anyway,
that they've been crushed and although they've been crushed, they haven't fully
been squeezed. The juices haven't come out yet, although they've been crushed.
והכא נמי כמי שחוסרים דיכה דמי. ve'hacha nami ke'mi she'chusarim dikah dami.
And this case of the משנה where you have the big beam
on the grapes and the olives, he said to me that seems
to be you can't prove that those things... we're talking about the
case where those things have been sufficiently crushed. So therefore, just because
רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael was lenient in the case about the, you
know, about the garlic and about the wheat and about the unripe
grapes, he was lenient because we were talking that they've been very,
very well crushed before שבת. But the case of the משנה, it's
not so clear they had been very well crushed and therefore that's
not such a good proof. And I would rather therefore turn to
רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer who explicitly speaks about things, the juices that
come out and says that it's not a problem. So where are
we with all of this? We have the case of the beam
on the olives and the grapes where even בית שמאי is not
bothered with it. As I told you before, that was an ancient
teaching that everybody said that that was okay. So בית שמאי somehow
has to allow for that to be an exception. But why is
it an exception? What's the reason? So גמרא says the reason is
because even as it continues on שבת, if you were to do
it yourself, it would not be חילול שבת. Chillul Shabbat. So בית
שמאי is only concerned with starting a process that on שבת would
be חילול שבת Chillul Shabbat if you were to do it. Here
if you were to do it, it would not be חילול שבת.
Chillul Shabbat. Why not? So we now see different תנאים Tannaim that
basically say once something is already crushed before שבת and the juices
continue to come out, you can drink from those juices. What does
that prove? It proves we're not concerned you'll come to squeeze from
it. If we let you drink from it, if we let you
drink from it, maybe you'll be eager to get it and you'll
come to squeeze from it. Obviously those תנאים Tannaim that say you
can drink from the juices feel that even were you to squeeze
from it, it would not be חילול שבת. Chillul Shabbat. Okay, and
why not? Since the juices were to come out anyway and your
squeezing is just hurrying the process, according to these תנאים, Tannaim, that
would not be חילול שבת. Chillul Shabbat. And that explains בית שמאי's
reason.
That's only if it's squeezed well.
Yeah, only if it's crushed well beginning ערב שבת, correct.
Okay, so basically our משנה then when you're putting these beams on,
it's because the grapes were already crushed very well.
Right,
at least well enough according to each תנא Tanna what they required.
Okay, so yes. So now the גמרא just wraps this up. הורה
רבי יוסי ברבי חנינא כרבי ישמעאל. Hora Rabbi Yose bar Rabbi Chanina
ke'Rabbi Yishmael. Rabbi Yose bar Rabbi Chanina ruled like Rabbi Yishmael
that the juices that come off are okay. Now,
שמן של בדדין ומחצלאות של בדדין, shemen shel badadin u'macha-tzla'os shel badadin,
oil
of the oil press and the mats used like the carry things
for the oil press. And these presumably are things
that are... well, the mats might be either used in a professional
thing, so they maybe are כלים that are used
for specifically for a professional use. And the issue about the wine
is a little bit debated about רש"י Rashi and תוספות. Tosafot. רש"י
says the wine is like some goop... not wine, oil, goop oil
that got caught in the corners. תוספות Tosafot says we're talking about...
let me just check תוספות Tosafot again, oh, yeah, the problem is
is that it's oil that ran off
while you were crushing the olives on שבת. While the beam was
crushing olives, the oil ran off. Is the oil, like we said
before, מותר or אסור? asur? So one reason we said the oil
that runs off on שבת could be אסור asur is you'll come
to crush the grapes, but the other reason might be a נולד
nolad issue. It's like a new thing has been created. Okay, and
the mats, that might be a similar מוקצה muktzeh issue because those
are things that are designated for this type of a use in
this מלאכה context. So what's the הלכה? halacha? So it says like
this: רב אסר ושמואל שרי. Rav asar ve-Shmuel shari. רב Rav says
it's not acceptable, שמואל Shmuel says it's permissible because there's basically debate
that רב Rav basically sides with a תנא tanna we'll see that
has a very broad definition of מוקצה, muktzeh, and שמואל Shmuel sides
with the תנא tanna that has a very narrow definition of מוקצה.
muktzeh. So שמואל Shmuel is not bothered with it, I don't consider
the juices that come off a נולד, nolad, and the mats, even
though they're set aside for professional use, they are not מוקצה. muktzeh.
אמר רבי נחמן, Amar Rabbi Nachman, similarly, עז לחלבה, eiz le-chalbah, if
you have a goat set aside for its milk, ורחל לגיזתה ve-rachel
le-gizatah and a sheep for shearing, ותרנגולת לביצתה ve-tarnegollet le-beitzatah and a
chicken to have its egg, ותורי דרדיא ve-torei de-radyah and an ox
to plow, ותמרי דעסקא ve-tamrei de-is'kah and you have dates, but they're
not for you to eat, they're to bring to the market and
to sell. So you've all these things that are set aside for
some type of a professional use—the word isn't professional, whatever the use
is, anyway, business
use—and you weren't planning on eating from it. But then comes שבת
or יום טוב Yom Tov and you're hungry. So you want to
go into the dates, even though they were set aside for being
shipped to the market, okay, or you want to go ahead and
you want to—or יום טוב, Yom Tov, you want to שחט shecht
the sheep or שחט shecht the cow. What can you do? So
רב אסר, Rav asar, רב Rav says sorry, if you didn't set
it aside for שבת use, it's no good. ושמואל אמר מותר, ve-Shmuel
amar mutar, it's permissible. So again, שמואל Shmuel has a much narrow
definition of מוקצה. muktzeh. A few things that are really out of,
you know, fundamentally set off for שבת, those are מוקצה, muktzeh, but
you don't have to actively designate something for שבת. So therefore these
types of things, even though they weren't actively designated for שבת or
יום טוב Yom Tov use, you can go ahead and use them
on שבת and יום טוב Yom Tov if you see fit.
Okay, so now the גמרא says, וקמיפלגי בפלוגתא דרבי יהודה ורבי שמעון,
ve-ka miflague bi-plugta de-Rabbi Yehuda ve-Rabbi Shimon, and they argue the debate
of רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda and רבי שמעון, Rabbi Shimon, which is
a classic debate where basically רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda holds of מוקצה
muktzeh and רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon doesn't hold of מוקצה. muktzeh. Now
that's said very globally. רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon doesn't hold of מוקצה,
muktzeh, but it doesn't mean he doesn't hold it at all. We
basically פסקן pasken like רבי שמעון. Rabbi Shimon. But what it means
is he only holds of it in very narrow cases, as opposed
to רב Rav and רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda that would say that
in order to use something on שבת, you have to specifically designate
it for שבת use. And that's why רב Rav had a problem
by all these things, he also had a broader definition of נולד
nolad and so on. Let's just finish to the
משנה. ההוא תלמידה דאורי בחרתא דארגיז, Hahu talmida de-arei be-Chartah de-Arguiz, a
certain student taught in this place, חרתא Chartah of this man ארגיז,
Arguiz, כרבי שמעון, ke-Rabbi Shimon, like רבי שמעון, Rabbi Shimon, that there's
no מוקצה muktzeh on שבת. שמתיה רב המנונא, Shamtei Rav Hamnuna, רב
המנונא Rav Hamnuna put him into
חרם, cherem, נידוי. niddui. והא כרבי שמעון סבירא לן? ve-ha ke-Rabbi Shimon
s'vira lan? Why did he put him into חרם? cherem? We פסקן
pasken like רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon that we basically we don't have-
that, you know, מוקצה muktzeh is a very small category. So the
גמרא says no, באתריה דרב הוה, be-asrei de-Rav hava, it was רב's
Rav location. לא איבעי ליה למעבד הכי, lo ibba'ei lei le-me'evad hachi,
he shouldn't have done that, he shouldn't have פסקןed pasken against רב
Rav in רב's Rav location, and רב Rav פסקןs pasken like רבי
יהודה. Rabbi Yehuda. One last story. הני תרי תלמידי חד מציל בחד
מנא וחד מציל בארבע וחמשה מאני. hanei terei talmidei chad matzil be-chad
mana ve-chad matzil be-arba va-chamisha manei. There we'll find out later if
there's a fire, they allowed you to salvage some food and do
certain דרבנן carryings—take the food out of the house and take it
into the courtyard. So one
basket and he piled stuff up really, really high, and the other
used four or five baskets to carry the stuff and made four
or five trips. So which one is preferable? So one basket with
a huge amount or multiple trips with a small amount? So וקמיפלגי,
ka miflague, that was debated, and that's the same debate, בפלוגתא דרבא
בר זבדא ורב הונא, bi-plugta de-Rabba bar Zavda ve-Rav Huna, like another
debate of אמוראים. Amora'im. So it's obviously been brought in here, you
have one debate which parallels another debate. But since we were talking
about crushing the olives at the olive press, we spoke about these
issues of מוקצה, muktzeh, where רב Rav holds of a broad definition
and שמואל Shmuel, holds a narrow—and I should say by the way
the נולד nolad issue is very relevant because there's a serious question
about do you פסקן pasken נולד nolad when something is around but
changes form? Like can you make- like if you make ice on
שבת, is that a נולד nolad problem? Is melting ice or melted
water נולד? nolad? תוספות Tosafot here basically says that most of those
cases would not be נולד nolad at all. The only issue here
was the olive because it's a real transformation. It's not like the
juice, you know, it's really to turning something that was food into
juice. But anyway, and even there it's said it's a debate of
רב and שמואל, so that's very relevant for practical הלכה halacha issues.
But with this we'll end the debate of בית הלל ובית שמאי
Beit Hillel ve-Beit Shammai about all these processes that began on ערב
שבת and continue into שבת.